<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dead-man's testament: or, A letter written, to all the saints of God in Scotland fellow-heirs of the blessing with those in England: for a view of the present work of God against the mystery of iniquity and for unity and love amonst themselves, in this day of the Lord's mercifull dispensation, and of the judgement of the whore. By Thomas Wood, sometimes inhabitant of Leith, lately departed this present life. And supplied by one of his own countrey-men, a lover of the true spirituall Beautie of Zion.  Published by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Wood, Thomas, of Leith.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832549</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37023</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66947)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37023)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2104:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dead-man's testament: or, A letter written, to all the saints of God in Scotland fellow-heirs of the blessing with those in England: for a view of the present work of God against the mystery of iniquity and for unity and love amonst themselves, in this day of the Lord's mercifull dispensation, and of the judgement of the whore. By Thomas Wood, sometimes inhabitant of Leith, lately departed this present life. And supplied by one of his own countrey-men, a lover of the true spirituall Beautie of Zion.  Published by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Wood, Thomas, of Leith.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Evan Tyler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Leith :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With imprimatur dated: Novemb. 25. 1651.</note>
                  <note>Copy imperfect; title page stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37023:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DEAD-MAN TESTAMENT: OR, A LETTER WRITTEN, To all the Saints of GOD in <hi>Scotland,</hi> Fellow-Heirs of the Bleſsing with thoſe in <hi>England:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For a view of the preſent Work of GOD againſt the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity; and for Unity and Love amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in this day of the Lord's mercifull diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and of the judgement of the Whore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY THOMAS WOOD,</hi> Sometimes Inhabitant of <hi>Leith,</hi> lately departed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this preſent life.</p>
            <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſupplied by one of his own Countrey-men, a lover of the true ſpirituall Beautie of Zion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Leith</hi> by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:37023:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37023:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37023:3"/>
            <p>HAving peruſed this Book, Intituled, <hi>The Dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mans Teſtament;</hi> I do finde it to be Orthodox and ſound, and likewiſe uſefull for the Lords People, namely, thoſe to whom it is directed, I do therefore allow it forthwith to be Printed and Publiſhed. <hi>Given under my hand at</hi> Leith, Novemb. 25. 1651.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>TIMO. VVILKS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37023:3"/>
            <head>A LETTER, WRITTEN, To all the Saints of GOD in <hi>Scotland,</hi> Fellow-Heirs of the Bleſsing with thoſe in <hi>England, Grace, peace, and love, with a rich Increaſe of all ſpirituall and heavenly gifts, be plentifully multiplied upon all you the Iſrael of God for ever.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Deſire to write to you (dearly beloved) not in any conſidence of mine own ability, being ſo unworthy; but in the love and light of his Spirit, who is our wiſdome, our righteouſnes, our ſanctification, and redemption I deſire to ſay ſomething to you the ſons and daughters of GOD, as the Lord himſelf hath named you, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. For I know (beloved) even by experience in my ſelf, that in this day of the fierce wrath of GOD upon this Land, the working of his Divine Providence, in much love and mercy toward you, may be too much looked upon, even by you his precious People, with the dark eye of naturall reaſon and ſenſe rather, then in the clear light of the Spirit of Truth, as his love is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant with you in Jeſus. Becauſe of the great diſtreſs upon this Nation, and wrath over this People, and becauſe of your own ſufferings in your bodily condition with the reſt of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as alſo becauſe the outward glory of this National Church, and beautifull appearance of holineſs and worſhip therein, is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37023:4"/> now much defaced; Therefore even ye the freely Beloved of GOD, are in danger (looking naturally upon theſe things) to conceive hard and diſhonourable thoughts of your kind and mercifull Lord, as if he were not fully pacified nor well pleaſed with you, in his dearly beloved Son; but were yet pleading a Controverſie with you in his diſpleaſure for your Iniquities, as he is doing indeed with all the ungodly of the Land. But (Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) although ye ſuffer in your bodily condition with the reſt of the Nation, yet your ſpirituall condition is nothing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired thereby, nor the free love of your Welbeloved any whit diminiſhed: For thoſe ſufferings, which in the Juſtice of God are curſes to the wicked, are in the mercies of your God, turned unto bleſsings to you: They are the fatherly chaſtiſements of your gracious Lords Hand upon you, in abundance of love, for teaching you more of himſelf in the Spirit, and of his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Conſolations; and therefore they can do you no evill, but good. Your Fathers wiſedome and love, make all things work for your good: He hath delivered you out of the power of evill, and darknes, and tranſlated you into the Kingdome of his dear Son, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 13. where ye have your life hid with Chriſt in God, above the teach of either temporall or eternall evills; for by one offering, your Lord hath perfected for ever all you that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. And therefore rejoyce evermore in the comfortable aſſurance of his free love, even with ſtrong conſolation; for your Lord called you to have free acceſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, even with boldneſſe unto the moſt Holy Place, within the Vale of his Fleſh, and hath covenanted with you, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your ſins no more, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 18, 19, 20. What reaſon then (Beloved) have your hearts to be troubled or afaid for any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhadow of evils; for ye have your abiding in the ſhadow of the Almighty. And as for the decay of the glory of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Church, and Formality of Worſhip, wherein naturally we did too much glory, as did the Jewes in the Temple, I truſt (Beloved) your GOD will let you ſee, that in all this great and terrible Work, both he, and his Inſtruments have had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37023:4"/> thoughts of love toward you his dear People, and is only plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with all the prophane in the Land, for the abuſe of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Things, and purging all you his Saints (who are his true Church indeed, in whom he taketh delight to dwell) from much corruption and deformity of the multitude, that ſo yee may ſhine as Light amongſt a perverſe Generation: for the beauty of this Nationall Church (Beloved) hath not been that purely ſpiritual and holy beauty of the Immaculat Spouſe of Chriſt, and Kings Daughter, all lovely and fair within, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. And therefore, be not ye offended (dear People) although your Lord, for his own glory and your comfort, caſt down, or pluck up that which not himſelf by his Spirit, but men by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſdome or policy had builded or planted: Neither miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ye the working of his Divine Hand, as if he were robbing you his People of any of his own ſpirituall or heavenly Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of free love, which himſelf hath put upon you; for his gifts toward you in theſe things are without repentance. But as he is renting his holy Things from the prophane multitude of the Land, to whom men had blindly caſt them, and who care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly trod them under foot; ſo is he in much love purging you his peculiar People from theſe Nationall, Whooriſh or Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh Ornaments of worldly power and glory, humane wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and policy, and counterfeit holines, and worſhip where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ye were fallen in love, and much defiled: for the Myſtery of Iniquity hath been very depthly and deceitfully working in this Nationall Church, both in regard of her conſtitution or Members, being builded (by the Policy of men, rather then by the Spirit of our Lord Jeſus) of all the prophane multitude of ignorant Atheiſts, Witches, Blaſphemers, Drunkards, Scol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Mockers of Godlines in the Land, under the name of a true Reformed Church of Chriſt, and a communion of the Faithful; and in regard of that confuſed, mixed Power and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment, under the name of a true Spirituall Church-power and Government of Chriſt, wherewith this Multitude was ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and governed; And laſtly, in regard of that confuſed or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37023:5"/> mixed Doctrine and Worſhip, wherewith this Multitude was taught, and wherewith they prophanely worſhipped, or rather highly provoked the Lord to anger: for alac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (beloved) this beauty of this National Church, hath conſiſted more in Multitudes of People, Humane Power and Policy, and forms of godlines in Worſhip, then in any reall beauty or work of the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus; For the Office-bearers of this Church, not contenting themſelves (as did the Apoſtles) with ſuch a number of you the Saint, to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Members of their Church-Communion or Body, as it pleaſed the Lord Jeſus to ſeparate out of the worldly Multitude, and call into a Church Communion, by the power of his own Word and Spirit, neither with that alone ſpirituall and divine power of him who is our Noble Ruler, left us in his Teſtament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to govern his own Spouſe in ſpirituall and holy beauty, as ſeparate from the World; but that the Church might have ſome appearance of glory in the eyes of the Multitude, and that their perſons might be holden in admiration by all men, becauſe of advantage, theſe Office-bearers thought fit to have all the whole Nation to be Members of their Church. And becauſe it was impoſſible for them, as the Lord's Miniſters, to rule thoſe by the power of the Word, who had never found the power of the Word, or to govern the ignorant Multitude, as Members of the Church, by the ſpiritual or Church-power of Chriſt, whom he himſelf had never brought into be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers by his ſpirituall power, therefore they were neceſſitate, (otherwiſe the Church could not ſtand in a Nationall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution) to joyn to their Eccleſiaſticall or Church-power, the Temporall power of the Civill Magiſtrate, for governing the Church, and compelling all the multitude of Fornicators, Whoremongers, Drunkards, Blaſphemers, Brawlers, Scolders and Calumniators (Fighters excepted, as not belonging to Church-cenſures) to appear before their Seſſions and Synods, for giving ſatiſfaction, although not to GOD (who appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth no compelled ſervice) yet to the Church or Miniſtery,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37023:5"/> by extorted verball acknowledgment of ſin, making their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance upon the Pillar ſeverall Sabbaths before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; which few or none would perform, till they were compelled thereto: And ſo, making a confuſed mixture of both Powers, Spirituall and Temporall, imploying the Civil Power in the government of the Church, and the Miniſteriall or Church-power in the government of the State, what they could not do by the Word, they performed by the Sword, for confining all to their iudgment, and for ordering all the whole unreformed Multitude, in one Church communion and Body, caſting the holy things of the Houſe of GOD, prophanely and confuſedly unto all. And ſo (beloved) whereas GOD hath proclaimed a perpetuall enmity between the Seed of the Woman, and the Seed of the Serpent, theſe men would make agreement betwixt them: But what communion hath Light with Darknes, the beleever with the unbeleever, or the Temple of GOD with Idols, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. And theſe things being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered (dearly beloved) it may appear to all you who are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually minded, that this Nationall Church-government and power, whereby it was acted over all People, hath not been the purely Spirituall and Divine Power of our Lord Jeſus, which he himſelf (upon whoſe ſhoulders is the Government) hath left us in his Teſtament or New Covenant, whereby to rule his own Church, but hath rather been worldly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; or like that deteſtable, counterfeit, mixed Power of that many-headed Beaſt, or Man of ſin, who by taking to himſelf the power of both Swords Spirituall and Temporall, hath by that falſe power, under pretence of Religion, and the Work of GOD, ſubjected all Nations to his obedience, tyrannized over conſciences, perſecuted the Saints, compelled all to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to receive his Mark; and ſo ordered all as one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion or body, under the name of the Catholick Church, and under that colour, hath deceived the whole Inhabitants of the World, ruling ambitiouſly over Peoples and multitudes, and Nations, and Tongues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. Which power and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37023:6"/> with all his falſe doctrine, and worſhip, <hi>The Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus (who cometh to be glorified in his Saints, and to be admired in all you that believe) is now to conſume by the Spirit of his mouth and by the brightneſſe of his comming,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.</p>
            <p>And as there hath been a deteſtable confuſion, and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous like mixture, of the civil and Eccleſiaſticall power, in the government of this Church, which hath maintained a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed mixture in her Members, ſo hath there been the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion alſo in her Doctrine: for by the doctrine that hath been publickly maintained, that this Church ſo conſtitute of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo governed by a mixed Power, hath been a Church moſt gloriouſly reformed, and worthy to be a Patern to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and that there ought to be in her no ſeparation, but all to be continued in one Communion. And although the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of all people upon civile occaſions, were lawfull and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, yet by this Doctrine, the meetings of you the Lords People, upon occaſion of mutuall conference, mutuall edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and comfort, were taught to be unlawfull, and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, and that the civile power might ſuffer none to enjoy their liberty in the Nation, but ſuch as were compelled to the judgement of the Church. Whereupon ſeverall of the Saints out of Conſcience, refuſing in ſome things, to conform, have been expoſed to ſufferings, and in the more ſubſtantial Point, the Preaching of Chriſt Jeſus, and free Juſtification by Faith, in him, hath been much obſcured, and darkened, by the doctrine of works, free Grace, and the everlaſting love of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and before all good Works, hath been ſo ſparingly, and darkly taught that almoſt, it could not be perceived, but the doctrine of the Law, and Works of Reformation, ſo largely and frequently holden forth, that almoſt nothing els could be heard, or known. In which confuſed mixture of the Law, Goſpel, Faith, and Works, in the point of Juſtification, and acceptance with God, the miſtery of iniquity hath wrought very deeply, and obſcurely, without being perceived, as it did in the time of the Appoſtles: for the comforts of the Word
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37023:6"/> have been applyed to all the multitude, upon their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of dueties, and the threatnings of the Word, likewiſe unto all the multitude, Beleevers, and unbeleevers, upon their failings in theſe performances. So that neither the miſerable condition of the wicked, hath been clearly holden forth, for caſting them down, neither the glorious condition of you the Saints of God, for building you up in the Faith, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing your ſtrength and comfort: For whereas the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane multitude ſhould have been plainly informed of the Law and curſe, in the full extent thereof, that they evidenced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be yet lying in bondage, in the eſtate of wrath and condemnation, under the power of the devill, and ſin; and therefore could not be eſteemed members of the reformed Church of Chriſt, nor of the number of Gods people, but by the contrary, the whole prophane multitude, who evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced themſelves to be open blaſphemers of God, and mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of you his people, and of all ſincerity and Godlineſſe, hath been taught and denominat, by this doctrine, to be Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people of God, faithfull Brethren, faithfull Siſters, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the true reformed Church of Chriſt, and of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, to whom the Seals of the Covenant aright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appertained. And as the condition of the wicked hath not been holden forth, but a crying, Peace, Peace, to whom there was no peace, ſo neither hath your condition, who are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, but as the Promiſes have been applyed, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane multitude, as one body with you, ſo the threatnings have been applyed to you, as one body with them: for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the bleſſing of the Goſpel, abundance of Grace and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Righteouſneſs, and free unchangeable Love, ſhould have been plainly holden forth, and applyed to you his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious People, only upon your embracing of Chriſt, and the free Promiſe by Faith, without, and before all good Works, <hi>Ye being freely juſtified by Grace, without the Works of the Law,</hi> Rom. 3. But by the contrary, the Law, and wrath have been applyed to you, with the prophane body of the land, and ye
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37023:7"/> have been taught as one body with them, that becauſe of your breach of Covenant, and failings in Reformation, and dueties, your God was not yet pacified with you, but was yet provoked to anger, and entring in controverſy with you, for your ſins, as with the reſt of the land, as if the Conſtancy of Gods Favour and Love, which he hath ſworn and promiſed to you, depended upon your performances, or Works of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. And as by this preaching of promiſes, upon perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, the wicked have been hardened in their courſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, in hearing the Word, Singing of Pſalmes, receiving the Sacraments, and ſuch like, being thereby eſteemed holy, both by themſelves, and the Miniſtery, and to be members of the Church, ſo likewiſe by this preaching of threatnings, upon your failings and infirmities, even ye the Lords people, (whom the Son hath made free indeed) have been keeped in much weakneſſe and bondage, and in a legall temper, under continuall fears and terrours of Gods diſpleaſure, and anger to the great weakning of your Faith; and diminiſhing of your Spirituall Strength, and comfort. Of Good Works, it is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, muſt be taught, but not as proceeding from fear of wrath, and diſpleaſure, for not performing thereof, but as proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Strength of God in us, thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ugh the aſſurance of his conſtant Love: <hi>For this love of our God increaſeth our joy, and this joy of our Lord, in us, is our ſtrength againſt ſin,</hi> Neh. 8.</p>
            <p>And as there hath been a confuſion in the members, and the government, and the doctrine, ſo hath there been in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of this Church: for this it is evident, that a worldly, carnal, and corrupted people can perform nothing (whatſoever they pretend) but a worldly carnall and corrupted worſhip. They cannot worſhip in Spirit and Truth: <hi>For the naturall man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth not the things of the Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. And therefore, if it be granted, that many of the people maintained to be members of this Nationall Church, and Performers of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in ſinging of Pſalmes, receiving the Sacraments, were but a worldly and carnall people, not acquaint with the life
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37023:7"/> of God, nor with the Miniſtery of Faith, then it followeth, that much of the worſhip performed by this nationall Church was but a carnall, corrupted; and ſinfull worſhip, deteſtable in the eyes of the Almighty: for, whatſoever is without Faith, is ſinfull, and abominable. And therefore the Lord hath been highly provoked, by the carnall, and faithleſſe worſhip, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the multitude, in our Solemn Aſſemblies: <hi>For the ſacrifices of the wicked are an abomination to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, beloved, that which much hath ſerved to fill up the cup of the Lords wrath, againſt this nationall Church, hath been in taking the Covenant: for the Miniſtery not truſting the Power of God, in the hearts of his Saints, for defending his Truth, thought good (as going down to Egypt for help) to combine all the whole Nation together, as one body, one Church, in that ſolemn band, wherein all the ignorant mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, who knew not what they were doing, were taught by the great and ſolemn Oath of God, to proteſt. Firſtly, that they had long and duely examined their Conſciences, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of true and falſe Religion. Secondly, that they were now fully perſwaded by the word, and Spirit, in the Truth of Religion. Thirdly, that under all the pains contained in the Law, and danger both of ſoul and body, in the day of Gods fearfull judgement, they ſhould defend the Truth of Religion. And was it not evident, (Beloved) that the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of this land, invited by the Miniſtery, to enter into that ſolemn Covenant, had never examined their Conſciences, in matters of true and falſe Religion; Neither were they ever perſwaded by the Word, and Spirit of God, in the Truth of Religion; and therefore could never defend that which they knew not: for the naturall man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God. So that, in binding themſelves by ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath, under ſuch horrible pains, to defend that which they never knew, they bound themſelvesover to the curſe of the Law, wherein the Miniſtery was cheefly inſtrumentall. The leaders of this people have cauſed them to erre, and they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37023:8"/> that are led of them are deſtroyed. And therefore the bloud of the ignorant multitude, ſo engadged by their leaders, and thruſt forth by them, as ſheep to the ſlaughter, for defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that whereof they had no knowledge, lyeth heavily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heads of the Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Concerning the Aſſemblies of this Church: Ye know (beloved) how corrupt, mixed, and confuſed they were; and that in theſe reſpects. Firſtly, in reſpect of their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency. It is much to be admited upon what accompt Church-Aſſemblies were, ſo frequent in this Nation. We can finde no preſident for it in Scripture: No more is read, but of the Aſſembly at <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 15. and of <hi>Pauls</hi> calling the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> together, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. v. 17. It cannot be denied, but the Church now and then, may call Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, upon ſome grave and weighty occurren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or other; whether it be, <hi>v. g.</hi> for diſcuſſing and compoſing matters of controverſie, as did the Councell at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or for ſome ſeaſonable, extraordinary and neceſſary word of exhortation and admonition. Upon which accompt, the Elders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> did meet. But I would fain know upon what accompt be their weekly Presbyteries, half-yearly Synods, yearly Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſemblies, and continuall Church-Commiſsions in this Land. Is it imaginable there can be fit matter for ſuch frequent meetings? No verily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What Caſes of Conſcience in finding out the poynt of juſtification, and matter of controverſie, in diſcovering the Myſtery of Iniquity have provoked ſuch meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? What grave and extraordinary word of admonition hath flowed from them, ſo often as they have been called? Or ſhall we think, the Lord's people (whom we judge, the the onely fit object and ſubject of Church meetings) ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, ſo backward, and ſo unruly, that they ſtand in need of ſuch frequent Aſſemblies? We dare not think ſo, unleſs we ſhould impung, their willingnes in the day of the Lords power, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. Their cheerfulneſs in obedience, by the love of Chriſt, which conſtraineth them, and the terrour of GOD, whereby they perſwade men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and the eminency of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37023:8"/> their knowledge, (being all taught of GOD, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 54.) whereby none of them needeth to teach another; but all of them know the LORD, from the higheſt of them, to the loweſt of them, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 31. That which engageth them to their duty, is the law put in their inward parts, and written in their hearts. It indeed, and not to multiplication of Church-Aſſemblies keepeth them loyall to the Crown royall of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Such Eccleſiaſticall powers uſe often to reſtrain Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty, but ſeldom, or rather never promove the juſt freedom and liberty of the Saints. Secondly, in reſpect of the matter propounded, and diſcuſſed in theſe Aſſemblies. Know ye not (Dearly beloved) in them nothing for the moſt part was to be heard, but needleſſe debates, and vain janglings? Any thing heard in them, was rather to miniſter Queſtion, then godly edification, which is in faith. How many tables and endleſs genealogies were heard amongſt them? which the Holy Ghoſt diſclaimeth. We learn no matter in Church-Aſſemblies from the Word, but grave Caſes of Conſcience, or matter of Controverſie, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. and of ſeaſonable and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary admonition for the good and edification of the Church <hi>Acts</hi> 20. But the LORD knoweth the Aſſemblies of this Church did not content themſelves therewith, but went far out of their ſphere. They could away with nothing ſo much, as to examine the Books of Seſſions, Presbyteries, Synods, and Commiſsions. They were not aſhamed to rob the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of his right, as their due. Nothing could ſatisfie them, but proceeding againſt Fornicators, Malignants, and all ſuch delinquents; as if they, and they onely had had right to the temporall ſword. Nothing could be done in Parliament, but what was ratified and allowed by them. They puſhed indeed with the two horns of the beaſt: for the matter of ſuch Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, is an acting with both ſwords, Temporall and Spirituall. And to colour all this, there was a doing great wonders, by making fire come down from Heaven, on the Earth, in the ſight of men, in eſtabliſhing Popiſh Pennances, or mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentances. O! what deal of the Spirit, did they pretend in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37023:9"/> theſe things? And thus they deceived them that dwell on the earth. Thirdly, in reſpect of the manner of proceeding in theſe Aſſemblies. It is known, they carried on things in a State-way, and not in a Church way: They did not take every thing to the Law, and the teſtimonie, but they diſputed every thing as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſtanding cloſe by formalities, Law quirks, and Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Conſtitutions i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not of State alſo as the grounds and wayes of their procedure. They did not proceed, becauſe <hi>it ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to them, but becauſe it ſeemed good to them,</hi> and was according to the Acts and Practice of the Church. Oh! was not this the over-word in, and touch-ſtone of theſe Conventions. Fourthly, in reſpect of the Members of theſe Meetings indeed they were anſwerable to their National Church; ſuch as were Members of the one, ſo of the other. And it can not be forgotten, how their Ruling-Elders did not only ſit as Ciphers in them (the Miniſters taking all upon them) but alſo they had no more Office-power, but <hi>pro tempore,</hi> yet I can ſee no reaſon, why all other officers of Chriſt's Church, ſo wel as Miniſters, may not injoy their office-power, <hi>vel ad vitam, vel ad culpam.</hi> And for my ſelf, I ſaw no uſe they made of them, but to carry on things by plurality of voices, as if the matters of Chriſt's Houſe had depended from the conſent and opinion of men, &amp; not from his own authority, according to the Word and Spirit. Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly, in reſpect of the power they did arrogate to themſelves: What they did, they did not as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, but as Court-Judicatures; they did not proceed by way of advice and counſell, and upon this accompt, <hi>for it ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, and to us,</hi> but by way of command; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>We enact and ordain.</hi> Sixtly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in reſpect of their outward pomp &amp; glory. O! how much were they backed with the powers of this World? And it is obſervable, theſe Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of late, did begin with the acceſſion of the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner thereto, <hi>An.</hi> 1639. and I hope their pride hath periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the acceſſion of the Vice-Roy to the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, 1651. The reign and riſe of Claſſicall Power are from the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 11. and therefore it cannot but pariſh
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37023:9"/> with the earth. The fall of carnal &amp; worldly powers will beget its ruine. Seventhly, in reſpect of their tyrannie; O! how much did they lord over GOD'S heritage; they thought it their duty to Lord over their Conſciences, to plant over, and tranſplant Miniſters from them at random. And I beleive, the Lord, of late hath given them plantation, and tranſplantation, beyond what they deſired. They thought it no ſin, to reſtrict people to forms of worſhip. To emit Declarations, Catechiſms, and ſtinte formes of Family-Worſhip, and directions anent wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping in publick, in their own ſtinted and Presbyterian way, They made it their great buſineſſe; even as their lips onely had preſerved knowledge, and all had been obliged to lay what they ſaid, or rather to ſwear what they ſpoke. They thought it no Hereſie, to emit Acts againſt the private Aſſemblies of the Saints, and their going, from one firſt day of the week, to another, to hear thoſe Preach, of whom they expected moſt for Edification, although their Pariſh-Prieſt had been an idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, void of the Saving knowledge of God. They exhorted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance out of all, and whoſoever would not take their mark upon them, they reſtrained their Liberty, by bills of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and caſting them over into the hands of the State. Such indeed had not liberty to buy and ſell, amongſt them. Any who denyed their Acts, and did not idolize their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (of which they made a State-Engine, for eſtabliſhing worldly powers) was forthwith to be excommunicat. No wonder: <hi>For, though they had Lambes hornes, yet did they ſpeak as dragons,</hi> Rev. 14. 11. Eightly in reſpect of the proud title, they did aſſume to themſelves. They were not aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Popiſh-like to call themſelves the Church, even as if ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and knowledge had been only to be found amongſt them in their own accompt, they were the Inheritance and Church of GOD, by way of eminency and ſpeciall propriety. What is this, I pray you (beloved) but the Man of ſin, ſitting in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, exalting himſelf above God as God, or that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. Beware of this Whore (dearly beloved) and Come out of her, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37023:10"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  </hi> Muſt needs tel thee ſhortly what the Author of this Letter was, how far he proceeded in it, and how it came to my hands. The Author of it was a moſt Religious body, and much perſecuted for the Truth. He lived here in Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, in a moſt privat and mean condition. And though he was blinde in the eyes of his body, yet (as appeareth) not in the eyes of his minde. In him our Lord hath made it appear, that he perfecteth his praiſe by the mouth of Babes, and chooſeth the fooliſh things of this World, to confound the Wiſe. His purpoſe was to emit this (he did not fear to profeſs Chriſt openly, though many of the rulers, who beleeve in Him d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not profeſs Him becauſe of the Seribes and Phariſes, yet before he cloſed it, he gave up the ghoſt. And he wrote no more of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but till you come to that which is ſpoken <hi>Pag. 12.</hi> concerning the Aſſemblies of this National Church, which I have ſupplied, at the deſire of a Religious Officer of the Engliſh Army. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the interim know, I did read an imperfest and undigeſted Scroll of the Authors, wherein he had hinted at ſeverall of theſe things, concerning the foreſaid Aſſemblies, which I expreſs, <hi>viz.</hi> Their ruling by plurality of voices, their debating things of no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and paſsing by the out ſearching the Miſtery of Godlines, and of Iniquity, together with their imploying the temporall ſword of the Magiſtrate in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Chriſts Church and Kingdom. But I durſt not adventure to ſet down theſe things in the Authors own words and way, though I had once intended it: for he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and confuſedly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them being called by GOD from hence before he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, and had taken them to his ſecond thoughts. Upon which accompt I have digeſted the laſt part of this Letter, in mine own way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (though in nothing d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcrepant from his purpoſe) leſt had I done: other wayes (he having departed hence before he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the cloſe of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the laſt part of it, ſhould have been inferiour to the reſt, as poſſibly it is as yet. Howſoever (Dear Christian Reader) take thou my good, thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for my good ſay, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace this Letter kindely, and fare thou well.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37023:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
